all right so the idea is to want to
share where I think are two pretty
fundamental things that will I think
help make sense about what's going on
right now the first has to do with the
the nature of I guess psychology or the
way that we go about solving problems
and the second has to do with the way
that our society or our political
framework polarizes in events like
what's going on right now so the first
basic idea is this there is and has been
a whole framework for how we go about
being effective in the world
this is habits and ideas techniques
tools a whole set of psychological
assumptions about the epistemological
things like how we know what is true and
what is not true frankly the greater
part most of the frameworks of Western
science developed since Newton and
Leibniz first laid down some of the key
ideas that is awesome for doing things
like building rocket ships and taking
them to moon and bring them back or
putting on a Boeing 777 they can fly
across the world but is really really
really inappropriate for the sets of
things that we're trying to deal with
right now and I mean that in a in a
fundamental way meaning that the the
underlying epistemological assumptions
about the nature of what knowledge is
and how one goes about even asking
questions is contradictory that is it is
just the wrong tool now this this fact
raises enormous cognitive dissonance
particularly it raises cognitive
dissonance if you're really good at
using the old tool either because it's
you have high efficacy in it or because
it's led you to a position of success so
this goes to the second point
the first main theme which is that human
psychology and quite likely actually a
higher level abstraction nature of
complex systems in general is that
they're intrinsically conservative if
something has worked meaningfully for a
significant period of time it is just
the case that changing is usually a bad
idea
it's risky to try to change into this
work consistently for a long period
trying to think that it's like a basic
conservative principle and this is true
often enough in evolutionary history
that it is a pretty hard hardwired into
our into our genes and this is true by
the way also an individual psychological
level right so if you have developed as
a person and you build a certain set of
approaches and strategies that have
worked for a long period of time or at
least seem to work for a long period of
time your your baseline set of signals
will tell you not to stop doing that not
to change it if you change it change it
at the edges but keep the core intact
and this basic fundamental shows up all
over the place it shows up in things
like how hard is to make big changes in
your life
it shows the things like why it is that
we have a tendency to become addictive
because addiction is when that
conservative principle loses track of
what seems to be good for us and what
actually is good for us and the seeming
is so powerful that will continue to
reinforce and actually mount that to
behavior until we no longer can even
right so so hold there for a second and
now I'm going to move to the second part
and then fill in the blank so the next
big piece is that it appears to be the
case that there is a pretty strong
correlation between a basic personality
type and political leanings so
specifically there are two kinds of
personality types that have been
identified by coding detailed to the
framework and Franklin item particular
attached to it this is just
the language one is called the train is
called openness and the other trade is
called orderliness so openness is
something like the degree to which you
like to experiment in which you find
novelty itself to be viable and
interesting and so people who are high
in trait openness tend also to be
politically liberal and this is a pretty
high correlation between the two and
then by contrast orderliness is as do
the things like having pieces in their
place if you're the kind of person when
you have your your dinner you like to
have all the ingredients be separate in
their own place on the plate that is a
very orderly trait and people who are
high in trade orderliness and in
particular they're also low in trade
openness mean they don't really have any
intrinsic attraction of novelty they
tend to stick you in the direction of
being conservative and so this is
essentially quite important as just a
getting to know each other level because
we're talking about fundamental things
that give rise to personality upon which
political opinions are sort of epic
phenomenon so when you're engaging with
somebody who has is on the other side of
that you're actually dealing consider a
lot more foundational than just their
and their political opinions it's about
how they go about making sense of what
is good in the world which is deeply
tied to stuff like how they're actually
wired or at least core early
developmental stages now the key idea
here is that these two deep approaches
actually respond to fear differently
when things seem not to be working when
our social assumptions or social
frameworks or social ideas or social
institutions aren't working the
conservative impulse is to retreat into
orderliness which if it is in fact
frustrated will become reactionary which
is in fact to retreat into a hyperbolic
level of orderliness which is an
imaginary orderliness that is a sort of
an Elysium of Organists that they kind
of recall at an emotional level
by contrast the liberals will retreat
into openness which the hypertrophic
ation of that is in fact actually in
Santa
right insanity is the such a complete
separation from any consistency that
it's sort of a random search and I think
this is part of what's going on is that
the people who are high in in the
orderliness are pulling hard in this
direction and I've been getting
transformed into reactionaries and the
people who are hiring trade openers are
pulling in this direction they're
increasingly becoming insane and I don't
mean that
pejorative lending that is a description
of the what happens to the mental state
when it just begins to explore new
territory radically and this is deeply
evolutionary because the question being
asked of the tribe is do we stay at the
old watering hole in spite of many years
of drought or do we leave and try to
find a new watering hole in spite of the
fact that we'll probably die on route
that's a question we have faced many
many times in evolutionary time and this
is the polarity of how it pulls apart
and as pulling the fabric of society
apart now here's the interesting thing
that I want to bring to the to the
center there's a third Pole in this in
this continuum and these are the elites
the actual people who currently control
choice-making
now what's interesting about the elites
is they are intrinsically conservative
from the beginning part of the
conversation if you have been successful
for a long period of time using a set of
strategies and practices and techniques
in your own psychology how you adapt to
the world or the way that the world
institutions have adapted to you then
you are going to be intrinsically
conservative change is a bad choice for
you now what's happening to that is
they're holding here and the signal the
change of some sort must happen either
at pull in this way or a pull in this
way is going to land on them
last or that will be pushing hardest
against them before they break because
they have the most to lose if you happen
to be say Sergey Brin and you're the one
of the biggest winners there is of the
game a that is the process of falling
apart it's a really really hard choice
for you to make to leave the watering
opportunity to change in such a way they
may be giving up a lot of stuff it's a
long way to fall it's a hard fall for
most of us to go through
reboot to a full snow crash and
completely give up a lot of the things
that we've used to survive and thrive in
the world you know our money our
relationships that people who can count
on us that's the thought process that we
use to solve problems but if the if the
question being asked if the problem
being posed is exactly that then the
pressure will continue to build and this
is going to start throwing all kinds of
errors the people who are currently in
the position they are entrusted with
choice making with a necessity of making
good deep powerful choices are
simultaneously going to be
hyperbolically separated from their
capacity to make choices because what
got them to right the right to make
choices was that they were really really
good at playing game a but the choices
they're being made to ask our choices
that are in a new game which we can call
me in B and they don't have a framework
for getting to game B and traversing
from gaming to game B requires a crisis
which it makes no sense for them to
actually cross and that's a very painful
and very challenging position to be in
and so you can imagine that what's going
on right now
and what will continue to go on until
something resolved the crisis is that
there is a separation it's kind of a
rending in a ripping in that Britain
will continue to come up as it becomes
impossible for people not to get pulled
into it until eventually the some
fraction of the folks at the top pop and
they go through their own crisis
whatever they need to go through and
they can then transition to be on the
other side of this line or they don't